Hi, and welcome back to
another episode with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be
looking specifically at chirality.
In this particular episode of
chirality, we're going to be learning
how to find the chiral carbons.
So let's get into exactly
what we're looking at when
it comes to a chiral carbon.
The whole thing with chirality is
that these are optical isomers.
So they are stereoisomers.
So it's all about how are they
positioned in three dimensional space.
Versus a constitutional isomer, which
is just about how are you changing
where branches go or substituents?
So in order to do this, there's some
little quick little steps for us to be
able to try to remember how to do this.
The first thing is that carbons
need to have four groups
around them no matter what.
So whenever we are looking at this,
it needs to have four unique groups.
So when we count four, right, we need
to then check are they all unique?
Meaning, they all have to be different.
So a hydrogen is different than
a CH3 versus an OH or a one side
of the molecule versus this one.
We need to make sure they are different.
If they are, then this is chiral.
Now sometimes you're going to also
have it where you can have four
things and some of them are identical.
So we need to realize that chiral
is when you have four unique things.
And achiral, or not chiral, right, is when
you are ignoring groups that, whenever
you have three or less groups, so when
you're looking around that carbon, and
we're trying to count, like, all the
little bonds around it to three or less,
so you want to ignore things like double
bonds, CH3s, CH2, When you are looking
at these structures now, this might seem
a little confusing at first, but let's
take a look at an example and go through
these steps and we'll go through several
practice prompts to understand this.
Let's go, let's go look at it.
Let's identify the chiral centers
or chiral carbons or stereo centers.
There are several different words
that are used to determine this.
If you remember, the first thing
that we had to do is carbons need
to have four different groups.
So let's first try to identify those.
So if I'm looking at the following
structure, we can try to find the
carbons with four different groups.
So if I look at the CH3, for
example, it has three hydrogens
and then also one CH bond, right?
So that has four things.
Now, keep in mind though, it
needs to have four unique groups.
So what we're going to be doing
here is going from carbon to carbon
and looking at every single group.
So a CH3, does that
have four unique groups?
Well, three of them are
hydrogen, so the answer is no.
So that is not going
to be a chiral center.
So let's now move to our next carbon.
So let's take a look right here.
So if I look at this one,
what do we exactly do we see?
We got to count every single group.
So when, what do I mean when I say
that, right, is that we're counting This
chlorine here as a group, this hydrogen
here as another group, the CH3, and
then we are counting this entire side
of the molecule as the other group.
So we got four completely
different things, right?
You have a chlorine, an H, a
CH3, so all of those are four
completely different groups.
I'm just going to put
big part molecule here.
So we have all those four groups.
So what does that tell you is that
this particular carbon, this is chiral.
So generally with these classes, you put
a little star next to it to tell you, Hey,
when if this has a mirror image to it.
There's going to be another form of it
that exists because bonds can potentially
flip and change Being that they are
commonly shown as wedges and dashes.
So let's take a look at other carbons
in this molecule Is that the only one?
Well, let's go to the next one.
So if I go down to this carbon here Well
same general idea you want to count are
there four completely different groups?
So we have a hydrogen We have an OH, we
have the C double bond O, OH, and then we
have the entire top part of the molecule.
This is very similar to geometries, right?
You're trying to see, like, is
it a tetrahedral geometry, right?
So four groups, are they
all completely unique?
Which they are.
So what this tells you is that, hey,
once again, we got another chiral center.
Is this all the ones that we have?
Well, let's try to take a look.
So we have one more carbon we can
look at right over here on the end.
Now, is this one that we can count?
Well, how many groups do we have?
Well, we see we have one, two,
three groups on all sides.
So this is one that's achiral.
It's not achiral carbon.
When it comes to trying to label
molecules now, so whenever you have
a chiral carbon, that means the
entire molecule is also chiral.
So our molecule here is a chiral
molecule, and it has two chiral
centers, or chiral carbons.
Those terms can be used generally,
they can be exchanged, they
mean the exact same thing.
So two chiral centers, or carbons.
All right.
And they both start to show that.
Let's go through some several different
other examples to kind of illustrate this.
And we'll see if we can
keep, keep practicing this.
And this is something where I
go through these next examples.
Feel free to try to pause the video
and see, can you do it yourself?
Because that's the ultimate way
to understanding is by practicing
it as much as you possibly can.
Let's go on to our next few examples.
All right, let's take a look at
all these different examples that
we have where we are trying to
identify all of the chiral carbons.
So, what are we going to do?
Let's go from molecule to molecule,
and what we're going to see is,
can we go from carbon to carbon
and see if they are chiral?
Right here we have three
different carbons, so we have
one, two, three across the board.
So let's look at the first one.
Does it have four groups,
and are they all unique?
So if a lot of times these are
drawn as geometric or skeletal
structures, so we have to remember
that there are hidden hydrogens on
every single one of these molecules.
So let's put them in.
So if I kind of put on each one of
these carbons, I put a hydrogen in here.
So we see we have two hydrogens here.
We'll put our hydrogen on carbon
number two, and let's put our
hydrogens on number three as well.
So, once we do that, do we have four
unique groups on each of our carbons?
Let's look at number one.
So on number one, you can see
that you have two hydrogens
on this particular molecule.
So what that means is, it does
not have four unique carbons.
So we can toss out carbon number one.
If we move to number two, well, in
this case, well, let's take a look.
We have One group on the left, one
group up top, the hydrogen counts
as a group, and then you have
this entire group on the right.
So, now is this one a chiral carbon?
Well, this one is really tricky,
because yeah, it does have four
groups, and they look pretty different.
However, when it comes to a lot
of these, what we need to do is,
imagine you draw like a little
imaginary line down the middle.
And when I do that, notice how the
left hand and the right side, they're
identical to one another, right?
You have a CH2OH on the right
side, CH2OH on the left side.
So what that means is two of
these groups are identical.
So this one is not.
Actually, as a result, it's still
a chiral on this particular carbon.
So whenever something like this can
happen, chirality can be lost as a result.
So in this particular one, it isn't,
that carbon isn't chiral either.
So we actually, and being that
carbon number three is the same.
This one is an achiral molecule, so
that means that we don't have any chiral
centers, and that, that's okay, most
molecules they don't, so we always have to
kind of check, go from carbon to carbon.
So let's do the same thing here.
So if I do the first one, right, so number
one here, we see that we have three CH3,
we have three hydrogens, right, on CH3.
So that tells you, no, we're
going to immediately toss that
out, it is not for unique groups.
If I look on carbon two, well, okay,
this one might be a possibility
because one of the things that we're
looking for is do you see four bonds?
Does it have that tetrahedral geometry?
Are they all unique?
So let's see, we have a CH3, we have
the hydrogen that's here, the OH, And
then the C double bond O CH3 side.
So yes, we do, we have four
completely unique groups here.
So we can star that carbon for
ourselves and then determine, yes, we
actually do have a chiral carbon here.
So that's kind of the trick, that's
exactly what we want to do as
we're going through this molecule.
And the more you practice this, the
more you're going to be able to see,
hey, These are really quick to find.
Now if I look at carbon number three,
we only have three different groups.
So just to circle that for
everybody out there, right?
We have one, two, three groups, right?
We're only referring to
groups, not number of bonds.
It's just how many different
areas of electrons do we have?
So when we have three,
it cannot be chiral.
It needs to have that tetrahedral
geometry so we can toss that out.
And now what does this mean?
We have a chiral molecule.
with one chiral carbon.
Alright, just like that.
We will write that down for ourselves
that we do have this chiral structure.
Let's go on to the next.
So ring structures are a little different.
The big thing about these is that
you need to try to get an eye for
finding different chiral groups.
The things, the shapes that you want
to generally look for are whenever
you see the carbon structure have
that like Y shape, because it
means it does have four groups.
The fourth one is always
hidden by a hydrogen, right?
Whenever we do a geometric group,
we assume that we have hydrogens.
And we can show that here, right?
We can fill in our structure.
We can see, hey, this has a hydrogen here.
This is a CH3.
Uh, we can fill in all
those things for yourself.
And it's really good practice, especially
if you're new to organic chemistry, is
counting all of your chiral, not only
your chiral, but all of your hydrogens
as you're going through these structures.
So we'll fill these in.
We'll put all the hydrogens here.
And this is something that gives us an
idea of, okay, well, what kind of Where,
where are my chiral carbons because we're
filling in all those missing pieces.
So let's take a look at
our possible candidates.
Now remember, if they have two
or more hydrogens, toss them out.
If it's a double bond,
also we can toss it out.
So the only two that are possible
are this one here on the bottom
and the one with the chlorine.
Now let's see, are they chiral?
Let's verify.
So if we do the bottom one,
what we can see is that we
have a CH3, we have a hydrogen.
Now remember from before, we gotta
check both sides of the molecule.
So how do exactly do I do that?
Well, when it comes to this kind
of structure, we want to once
again try to draw an imaginary
line right down the middle.
And what we're trying to see is, are both
sides of the molecule, are they the same?
It's kind of like
comparing heads and tails.
Are they the same on the coin?
So when I do that, right, I have
one side here on the left, and
then let's use another color, and I
have a different side on the right.
Now, are they the same?
Well, on the right hand side,
we see that we have a chlorine.
On the left hand side we have a
double bond, so that tells you, yeah,
both of them are very different.
It's not like the example, the
first example, where, oh, they are
identical, these are different.
So this is a chiral carbon.
This can stay.
Now, we can do the exact same thing
for the chlorine structure from before.
Where hey, let's let's take a look at it.
Let's uh, try to circle all the groups.
So we have a chlorine We have a hydrogen
We're gonna draw a little line right
down the middle and what we see is
Oh The top half has a double bond
and the bottom half does not so that
star also can stay in the structure
That this is another chiral carbon.
So we this is chiral
with two chiral carbons.
Okay.
So let's write that down.
Chiral with two chiral carbons.
All right, let's take a look
at our last example here.
O' sorry, our second to last example.
Now, what about this one?
Well, same idea, right?
We want to look for that triangle shape,
try to look for three and four groups.
So the first one that comes to
mind is this one right here.
Now, being that it's the only one, all
the rest have two hydrogens, right?
So every single one of these have
two hydrogens on each of them.
So we don't have to worry about trying to
consider whether or not they're chiral.
But this one, on the other
hand, it only has one.
So this is possible.
Now, what about the two groups
on both sides of the coin?
Well, if I draw a little line
here, well, what do we see?
We have one side over here and
then another side on the right.
Are they the same?
Well, we have CH2CH2 on both
sides and they meet in the middle.
They're identical.
So what that tells you is that
two of the groups are the same.
So this is going to be
an achiral molecule.
So it's really good to be able to.
Get that skill down.
Symmetry.
If you see a symmetrical molecule, it
should raise a little red flag that, hey,
double check it because anything with
symmetry, a lot of times it's not chiral
because of that symmetrical look to it.
It doesn't have that optical property.
Now, what if I go to a big one?
So, what if I go to something like this
that's kind of very similar to glucose?
So, if I have this, we gotta go through
the same idea as carbon to carbon.
Now, we can, we can throw
out a couple things quickly.
If we look on here, on this carbon on the
far right, you see that C double bond O.
So, that tells you, oh,
there's only three groups.
So, we know that's not gonna be one.
So let's put a little red X there.
Not a choice.
Same thing with the one on the far left.
It has two CH2s, so also not quite one.
Let's fill in the hydrogens
for every other one in the
middle of the chain, right?
You see that all of these different ones
They all have one hydrogen, which is
kind of the thing you're looking for.
If you see that little tail of a
hydrogen, that might tell you it's chiral.
Not guaranteed, but most likely.
So if we look at, let's say,
the first one here on the left,
well, what exactly are we doing?
Well, we see we have one group here.
We have the hydrogen.
the OH, and then our other
group is the whole entire side
of the molecule over here.
That whole thing is a group.
So what does that tell you
that, hey, this one is chiral.
We have one chiral carbon,
at least on this molecule.
So the second you have one chiral carbon,
now the whole molecule is chiral as well.
So if we go to the next one, well, it's
going to be the same general idea, right?
You can see, hey, this
one also has four groups.
So we have one, two, three.
Four groups.
Oh wait, I had put four on that side.
Miss, uh, miss side count.
Miss did it.
So we have 1, 2, 3, right?
The big group on here.
And then we also have.
four groups on this side, right?
We have four completely different things.
So that is chiral.
So what this is kind of getting to is
that every single one of these molecules
in the middle here are all chiral.
So we have three, four,
And five, chiral centers.
Okay, tips and tricks to
spot chiral centers fast.
A lot of times you have standardized tests
that are timed, and you don't have maybe
that time to count every single group.
So the first thing you're always
going to do is you're looking
for the following pattern.
In a lot of the geometric
structures that we did earlier,
you saw that triangle pattern.
So the R's just tell you some, it's
some group, whatever functional
group or alkyl group it is.
If you see that pattern, usually what
that means is that the fourth group
that's here is always that hydrogen tail.
So keep track.
If you see three, most likely
there's, there's a good chance, right?
You still got to count, you just got to
look at your groups, but it's something,
if you can see that quickly, It's going
to save you a lot of time if you have
that hydrogen that's hidden here, right?
You want to check is there a hydrogen now?
The other one is if there's a four
group already on your structure, which
whether it's a condensed structure or a
complete structure This is something to
look for because you want to check are
all four of them Are they different if
they are there you go You got a chiral
group now with a lot of these the thing
you can ignore you can ignore CH because
you have those multiple hydrogens.
They're one of the common things
that students will look at first
because they think, Hey, I got this.
I got four groups.
They have to all be different,
they have to be unique, right?
Every single thing is unique,
and that's the big thing.
So also, throw out identical groups.
So what I mean by that is, let's say
if I had the following structure,
uh, where I have a carbon with a
CH3, CH3, hydrogen, and an OH, right?
Now, being that I have
these two CH3s here...
They are both identical,
so they can get thrown out.
So really try to pay attention to
anything that's symmetrical, so
meaning it's the same on both sides.
If that happens, there's a good chance
it's probably not going to be chiral,
because if there's any symmetry, that
means the two groups are the same.
So draw the little lines
down your structure.
It's something that will help
you identify these things.
Let's try to take a look at some bigger
molecules, some things that we'll find
in pharmaceuticals and see if we can
get our chiral carbons really quick by
identifying these, using these tips.
So we're not going to be counting.
We're going to be looking for those
particular trends in structures.
Let's take a look.
Okay.
So if we want to identify chiral
carbons and things like pharmaceuticals,
Now, why is this so important?
Well, when it comes to the pharmaceutical
industry, a lot of times we need to
make sure we have the right chiral
chemical that's being sent out to
patients and people and consumers.
If it's the wrong one, a lot of times
this can have very harmful side effects.
So let's look at ibuprofen.
Well, first thing was, is try to quickly
identify anything that was a three,
four group, um, within a molecule.
we can throw out double bonds, meaning
that entire benzene ring in the middle.
ignore it, right?
Because you know that that has those
double bonds, it doesn't have four groups.
So the ones that kind of come to mind
are here, here, here, and here, right?
So looking at the middle.
Now it doesn't mean that these
are all chiral, but they all
have three or four groups.
So this is something that,
hey, are any of these it?
Let's start at the top right.
Well, this one is a C double bond OH.
So right off the bat, we can say, nope,
that one is not a chiral If we go to the
next one, well, we see a carb, we see our
carbon, and we can count our groups, so we
have one, Two, three, and then we have the
entire left side of the molecule, right?
So those are four groups.
So what does that tell you?
That you have a chiral carbon
right here in the middle.
So what that means we have one.
So that means that
ibuprofen is chiral so far.
Let's take a look over here.
So if I do the first one on the right,
now notice that we have a C2CH2's here.
So what does that mean?
Throw it out.
You got two groups that are
identical to each other.
So that means that this is a big red X.
This one is not chiral.
Now this one on the other
hand, is this one chiral?
Well, I have, look what
I have here are two CH3s.
So what does that tell you?
Two of them are the same.
So that means once again,
we can ignore this group.
And we can draw a little red X for
ourselves saying that, oh, this is
not chiral, so the only thing you have
is one chiral carbon on ibuprofen.
However, even though you
have that one chiral carbon,
it's still a chiral molecule.
So we can label it as chiral.
So you just need one.
Now let's look at naproxen.
So naproxen is another really common
drug that's used for pain relief.
So, once again, are there any
three, look at those triangles.
We can see the two benzene rings, right?
So we can, or the two aromatic rings.
So we can toss those out, right?
That's not going to be a choice.
We see on the end here, we
have a CH3, that can go away.
We also have another CH3 up here.
There is this one right
here in the middle.
It has that shape.
So we can fill in the hydrogen.
Is this a chiral carbon?
Well, the answer is going to be yes.
We have a CH3.
We got this entire portion of the
molecule on the right hand side.
We have the hydrogen.
And then we have the entire
ring structure that's over here.
Right?
That's another side of the molecule.
So, you have four completely different
colors, four different bonds, so this
means that we have a chiral carbon in
the middle, um, of our chiral, of our
structure, so that means that naproxen
is chiral, and we have one chiral center.
And that's something that we look for,
because with naproxen, if, depending
on which version you have, one of them
will be a pain reliever, the other one's
a liver toxin, so there could be huge,
huge benefits in making sure we have
the right one within our population.
I hope that this video helped
you and be able to better your
and understand your skills on
how to figure out chiral carbons.
Um, please feel free to rewatch
and pause it and to share it to
help, to help other students.
And if you did like it, then please
hit that like and subscribe button
because there's going to be more
content continuously coming out.
We've been posting one to three
videos every week and that's
something I  plan to keep doing.
And thank you so much for
watching and look forward to
seeing you all in the future.
Bye now.